# Yoseph Datu Adiatma

### **Qualification Summary**

PhD in Earth Science with experience in sedimentology, chemostratigraphy, isotope geochemistry, and numerical modeling. My research centers in reconstructing changes in geologic processes using geochemical proxies (e.g.,  $\delta^{13}$ C,  ${}^{87}$ Sr/ ${}^{86}$ Sr,  $\delta^{44/40}$ Ca,  $\delta^{7}$ Li,  $\epsilon_{Nd}$ ) and their roles in shaping the macroevolution of life on Earth.

#### Education

Fall 2023	PhD in Earth Science, The Ohio State University
Fall 2018	MS in Earth Science, The Ohio State University
Spring 2014	BS in Geology, Institut Teknologi Bandung

# **Academic Appointments**

2024 - present Postdoctoral Research Associate, Florida State University

Perform geochemical analyses (I/Ca, Fe speciation) on Paleozoic-aged

sedimentary rocks to reconstruct the paleoredox states of Cambrian - Ordovician

seawater.

Fall 2023 Postdoctoral Research Associate, The Ohio State University

Performed calcium isotope analyses ( $\delta^{44/40}$ Ca) on Paleozoic-aged carbonate rocks and developed numerical models to constrain the role of diagenesis in affecting

geochemical proxies in carbonate rocks.

2019 - 2023 Graduate Research Associate, The Ohio State University,

Collected samples, performed numerous geochemical analyses ( $\delta^7 Li$ ,  $^{87}Sr$ / $^{86}Sr$ ,  $\epsilon_{Nd}$ , Sr/Ca,  $\delta^{44/40}Ca$ ) on Ordovician-aged carbonate rocks, and developed a suite of numerical models to reconstruct changes in global silicate weathering and its

role in causing multimillion year climate cooling.

#### **Publications**

Peer-reviewed articles

Adiatma, Y.D., Saltzman, M.R., Griffith, E.M., 2024. Calcium isotope constraints

on a Middle Ordovician carbon isotope excursion. Earth and Planetary Science

Letters 641, 118805.

Avila, T.D., Saltzman, M.R., Adiatma, Y.D., Joachimski, M.M., Griffith, E.M.,

Olesik, J.W., 2022. Role of seafloor production versus continental basalt weathering in Middle to Late Ordovician seawater <sup>87</sup>Sr/<sup>86</sup>Sr and climate. Earth

and Planetary Science Letters 593, 117641.

2022 Conwell, C.T., Saltzman, M.R., Edwards, C.T., Griffith, E.M., Adiatma, Y.D.,

2022. Nd isotopic evidence for enhanced mafic weathering leading to Ordovician

cooling. Geology.

Adiatma, Y.D., Saltzman, M.R., Young, S.A., Griffith, E.M., Kozik, N.P.,

Edwards, C.T., Leslie, S.A., Bancroft, A.M., 2019. *Did early land plants produce a stepwise change in atmospheric oxygen during the Late Ordovician (Sandbian* ~458 Ma)? Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology 534, 109341.

#### Manuscripts in review / in preparation

in revision Adiatma, Y.D., Saltzman, M.R., Liu X-M., Wang, X-K., Edwards, C.T., Lithium

isotope and Ordovician weathering. in revision.

in review Wang, X-K., Liu, X-M., Husinec, A., Cao, C., Dera, G., Adiatma, Y. D., Lithium

isotope evidence for enhanced hydrothermal activity in the Jurassic

### **Selected Conference Abstracts and Presentations**

Adiatma, Y.D., Saltzman, M.R., Griffith, E.M., Haber, P.C., Braun, M.G.,

Edwards, C.T., Diamond, C.W., 2022. Calcium isotope constraints on the origin of the Mid-Darriwilian Carbon Isotope Excursion. Presented at the GSA Annual

Meeting, Pittsburgh, PA.

Adiatma, Y.D., Saltzman, M.R., Griffith, E.M., Haber, P.C., Edwards, C.T.,

Diamond, C.W., 2022. Calcium Isotope Constraints on Diagenetic Effects in Carbon Isotope ( $\delta^{13}$ C) Data: A Case Study from Middle Ordovician Carbonate Strata at Meiklejohn Peak, Nevada. Presented at the AGU Fall Meeting, Chicago,

IL.

Haber, P.C., Saltzman, M.R., Griffith, E.M., **Adiatma, Y.D.**, 2022. Early Mississippian calcium isotope stratigraphy and implications for conditions of carbonate deposition. Presented at the Joint Annual North-Central and

Southeastern GSA Section Meeting, Cincinnati, OH.

#### **Honors and Awards**

The Michael S. Johnson Outstanding Graduate Student Award, The Ohio State

University, School of Earth Sciences

2010 – 2013 Dean's List, Institut Teknologi Bandung, Faculty of Earth Sciences and

Technology

#### **Research Grants**

2020 Graduate Student Research Grants, Geological Society of America (\$2800)

2020 Grants-in-Aid, American Association of Petroleum Geologist (\$2500)

2017 - 2021 Friends of Orton Hall, The Ohio State University, School of Earth Sciences (range

from \$1500 to \$5000)

2013 L. Austin Weeks Grant American Association of Petroleum Geologist (\$500)

# Field Work Experience

2024	Trail Creek, Idaho, USA (12 days)
2019	Collierstown, Virginia, USA (1 week)
2018	Germany Valley, West Virginia, USA (1 week)
2018	Antelope Range, Nevada, USA (1 week)
2017	East River Mountain, West Virginia, USA (1 week)
2013	Tapin District, South Kalimantan, Indonesia (5 weeks)

# Professional Associations and Leadership Roles

Indonesia Association of Geologists (IAGI) -- Geological Society of America (GSA) -- American Geophysical Union (AGU) -- American Association of Petroleum Geologists (AAPG)

Student Representative to the Graduate Study Committee at OSU School of Earth Sciences (2021) Earth Science Delegate to the OSU Council of Graduate Students (2022)

#### Skills

Geochemistry and Mass Spectrometry

- Sr, Nd, Li, Ca column chemistry
- Basic operations and method development of thermal ionization mass spectrometry (TIMS)
- Basic operations of inductively coupled plasma optical emission spectrometry and mass spectrometry (ICP OES and ICP MS)
- Geochemical modeling

#### **Programming**

- Python
- Matlab

#### Miscellaneous

- Unix-like OS operations (Ubuntu, RHEL, FreeBSD)
- Version control software (git)
- High Performance Computing (HPC)